so
what was it like like what was your
experience uh
hosting 70 plus episodes of artifact
so first year was like a nightmare
it wasn't as
nice as you would imagine
[Music]
hello everyone welcome back to another
episode of the lab podcast how are you
all doing um today's episode is a
special one he has hosted over three
seasons and has hosted over 70 episodes
of heart attack with the god of god how
are you
hi anne good to be here
finally we made it
yeah it's been a while uh yeah we've
been in and talking um but yeah so
everybody wants to know this you know
every it's everyone's dream to host an
attack episode um so how did you get
into art attack was there an audition or
like what was the process of you hosting
artifact
yeah certainly there was audition uh
we had almost like one video we had to
send and then when they shortlisted the
people then they had to go to bombay to
disney and kind of have another audition
there um but it was largely uh you know
by luck i never planned to either join
media or host a show it was never in my
intention or rada
so when the opportunity came i just
you know i just applied myself without
much expectation
yeah and and yeah it went through so i i
kind of gave it a shot
and that's exactly it
so
what was it like like what was your
experience uh
hosting 70 plus episodes of art back
was it like
very professional or
just the aura around and the experience
that you had over the years
yeah definitely the setup was very
professional
because uh you know i mean if if a
company like disney is doing something
and art attack already is a old show
right yeah so it started off in 82 with
neil buchanan and
eventually um
it came to india like
in
all over the world it was being dubbed
in different languages and finally they
realized in 2010 uh a little before that
they might as well have new episodes
with local dialect and in hindi for
example right
um so first year was like a nightmare
it wasn't as
nice as you would imagine
for various reasons uh one is that art
attack was shot in argentina in buenos
aires not in india
because like i said when they decided we
need more episodes it was a worldwide
decision
it wasn't just the decision of you can
say
india so they were like 14 different
hosts who have 14 different languages
um and we were shooting heart attack for
all everyone so all that shooting
happened in buenos aires and not in
india so on one set everybody like all
the hosts were
yes yes yes that was the
but at different times of the year not
at the same time uh at one go there
would be uh
like two hosts one would do have a
shooting in the first half and one would
have shooting in the second half so that
was the setup there
and yeah so first first season was like
i was never a performer or a actor or
into theater
so this was a completely new medium and
definitely there is a lot of fear around
camera it's a unfair one because you
have to
interact with the inanimate object like
a camera
and it's extremely boring and also it's
not as exciting so the main skill is
being looking excited while talking to a
glass screen you know
yeah
everybody wants to know what did you do
after after that like
how did you progress your career after
that
uh so one great thing that happened like
most people uh assume that
fame itself is
the final
how do you say reward for a person who
works in media
um not for me for many people maybe
but
since it accidentally happened it was
never in my radar like i said so it was
never my desire point to work in a show
and even the what comes with the show i
was also not in much interested in that
which means people get to know you and
etc etc uh i like i love to have fun
with what i'm doing that's the first
premise
now that is what i was pursuing always
and
after right after art attack basically
it introduced me to
students and children as a audience
and that's that's the point when i
realized that what i really want to do
is i need to
keep learning and sharing what i know
with children
without attack the thing is it's
one-sided i'm on one front of the camera
and then students see me on video right
so there is no interaction as such
so that interaction is only possible if
i work live with them and therefore
that's the point in 2011 you can say
uh you can say one after one year after
shooting heart attack
is when i realized i would like to you
know keep
entering learning as a zone
and keep working working in that
scenario
so
yeah so first season like i said was a
nightmare second third season were a lot
of fun uh that's where i that's when
also you you get a skill and therefore
now you can play with it
the first year was all about learning
everything which was new
who would you say is your biggest art
inspiration like do you have a specific
person who inspires you
you might be disappointed but i don't
have
many inspiration in that sense
yeah
because see i like work of different
artists
but i generally don't follow
in that sense i do not follow anyone
i have my own thoughts i need to pursue
yeah and and therefore i'm kind of more
in my own head then i'm in someone
else's head you know and yeah therefore
because what i'm pursuing is not even
art
that's only heart attack that you're
talking about
but previous so if three years is heart
attack for example the rest of the nine
years uh
like 12 years of experience now so when
i rested our nine years is all around
students which also means uh my special
audience that i have chosen to work with
uh then there is education and learning
that i work with
so
all right so which means my inspiration
is uh there's a big batch of different
people who might consider my inspiration
yeah uh for different reasons of course
like some of them uh
who have worked around pedagogy and say
for example rudolf steiner
who uh gave a
new field of anthroposophy
um world of education has come out from
there so i follow world of education and
therefore i follow rodol steiner
at the same time i have my own other
spiritual guru um for example i follow
pranic healing so the the master who
introduced pranic healing i consider him
my technical guru in terms of
spirituality
then
it's not just art you no no no
yeah
because uh i am more mixed material than
art
and therefore uh i would be working with
wood like i have some wood lying right
behind me right here uh i work with a
lot of material and and i love to
express i love to repair so
art is not the only thing that i love
that's great yeah
like for example again as inspiration
you would say i would say tesla nikola
tesla would be one inspiration for me to
be
someone who dedicates their life into
their work so that and of course his
contributions are separate but as an
attitude
there and for example bruce lee for me
would be the person who would have
achieved the epitome of human body
capabilities yeah yeah uh like many
others but also
he had his own philosophy so so i have
these different figures whom i whom i uh
really look forward to uh in terms of
of course there are real life living
people also who might get inspired by
but uh
one loophole which i find which i try to
avoid is
when you're getting inspired by someone
be very specific about what
the inspiration is and stick to that
which means if someone's art is great
i i'm inspired that person as an artist
not as a human being
because being a human being is very
different you can be a great scientist
but a horrible husband or a father
you understand yeah so when you are
following someone you can't follow
someone blindly about everything in
their life
uh because then you're missing out on
the part of being human
yeah
so
is this something you regret um in your
career
so you might want to make people aware
about
i don't think i have any regrets
i've actually and i have not done my
career path
clinically or calculated wise okay
i've taken a lot of decisions which are
very
you can say spontaneous
gut feeling based on gut feeling when i
got opportunities i just act on it
and then i don't worry whether how it
whether it translates or not because my
job is done i was supposed to respond to
the opportunity that's all is required
and if it happens uh and if it gives me
a good feeling i go ahead if it doesn't
happen then it's okay of course there
are some disappointment you're like
that's perfectly fine
and therefore i've done a my my
background is such that
i work without attack that's the first
thing which i did after college so do
you understand
when you set a
uh your career path in that's
it can be a problem for a lot of people
because now they set the bar high for
themselves and they can't see themselves
otherwise because the first question
people your fans everybody will be
asking is oh you know how much you
earned and where do you live and so
there is a lot of lifestyle around the
media field correct
however there is no data to say that
everybody's supposed to be rich and if
you actually go down and seek what kind
of earning possibly an i.t professional
is earning a lot more than a lot of
actors and actresses
you understand because the thing is the
money involved there if you if you take
the total because they might end up
earning through one project
but maybe there are breaks of
no non-functioning or no work during the
year that's how a lot of freelancing
works especially in acting also if
you're lucky you get a lot of work if
you're not not lucky you get one or two
things in a year so it's a completely
unorganized sector
and um and therefore
yeah so my trajectory i've also for
example worked in school as a teacher
after heart attack i chose a role as a
teacher because i wanted to understand
my audience better and there is no other
way to understand an audience otherwise
but working with them directly so i
worked one year in ahmedabad in a
riverside school then i worked one year
in rural in a village school in
jaisalmer okay again so that i can gain
the experience of working in a village
school and how did i come about it is
like i asked my mentors and they're like
you know these all these schools are
there
and in the whole list there was one
school which was in the village
section so i kind of it kind of gave me
a spark and i chose that as a choice
uh and things it's not like you choose
and it happens to you even with
jaisalmer i was sending them email and
it was not being responded
so one fine day i just found them on
google map and i ended up in the school
and i told them i would like to work
with you
and
then i worked with them for a trial for
a week or two and then they were also
comfortable and confident so we then i
worked for one whole year in jail marina
rural setting
so in that sense uh i've never regretted
my my friends were worried they're like
why are you taking this there's no not
even money there's like why would you do
this
but people will not understand your
logic uh
so if it's important for my growth i
don't expect other people to see or
understand why it is important for my
growth
i get that feeling and i act on it and i
don't waste time unnecessarily
right so therefore
i have a like in that sense i have a
huge spectrum of work experience and
personal experiences
yeah which are um yeah
so no regrets
yeah that's great
when it came to uh working anywhere
or while teaching or
just
any job you've done including our attack
did you have any bad work day and what
did you take away from
it bad work day yes many days were bad
work days
you also go through you can say
social discrimination
which did happen in some form in art
attack also shooting in so they were
just weird people sitting and who were
kind of managing
our team was pretty good um which means
almost everyone in the whole team was
amazing
while shooting heart attack just because
of one or two people who were the
decision maker they made our life really
difficult there uh unnecessarily i would
say uh and not even professionally it
would like
you know how
how having a bad day is a psychological
terror it's not a technical error
okay so therefore
but the thing is uh
what i learned is one thing is i learned
the hard way of how exactly shooting
happens because when i was shooting for
our dragon when the things were tough
i thought that's how it is because i had
no other experience of working in the
industry right
so that's that's also one thing we have
to be careful about is
uh if things don't seem right then you
have to fix them because you might be
accepting them it's a norm it should not
be a norm
and therefore we we did uh say it much
later once we returned back and they
then the
disney team was like why didn't you tell
us before
so i told them i was the youngest player
there might i expect other people too
because i have no idea how things are
so yeah but i also learned that uh
slowly without attack of how to be
comfortable with the camera and the act
of performing
you're having fun with yourself that
it's uh only children can do that
it's a difficult thing for adults to
have fun with themselves okay yeah
so like a big piece of advice um
uh in a sentence or just a quote that
you really love that really inspires you
many quotes but i don't remember
honestly um
i would rather create my own but i don't
remember the quotes
one of one quote i do like um
which i do believe in two people have
mentioned this
uh objectively one is
elizabeth gilbert uh in her ted talk
elizabeth genius
and second is again nicola tesla and
they both are talking about that
ideas and creativity is not generated
within the body
all right it comes from somewhere
and
if you're aware of this process and if
you don't have that ego oh i'm
generating this idea and i am so cool
then it's a limitation to your
creativity but if you believe that the
ideas actually exist in the universe and
they come through you
so the better
mind body and heart you create the
better fertile land it becomes for the
ideas to flow through and of course the
the kind of ideas that will flow through
you are subjective to your
cognitive abilities and how you think
and what capabilities you have as a
human being so because certain things if
it does not fall into your perspective
perspective as a world will never come
to you
all right so when some people for
example they're like oh like if you go
with the conventional religious all
religious conventional bodies around the
world
they cannot accept the multiple genders
that are that's a reality in in modern
world right they will not it's because
they their thought process is so old
that they can never they don't even know
it can exist and they can't even accept
that it can exist
and they're not strong enough to break
their perception
so a person like that can never have
ideas around that particular section
similarly if you want to be technically
sound then your mind must work in a
little technical way
and if you want great creative ideas to
come through you you have to understand
that creativity is not a
linear process
you have to have a very wide base with a
lot of abilities
like you have to be a jack of all
um and you can specialize in few things
but you really need to be a jack of all
so you understand such huge
i understand art i understand science i
understand bio chemistry i understand
human behavior i understand psychology
and so on and so forth and i understand
audiences and and mix and then when the
idea starts traveling through me it goes
through all those different filters
yeah right and then something will come
out
so the more stronger your filters are it
will filter everything nothing will come
out
but you need to be able to connect those
filters also so interconnection
keyboards
in your
self you know yeah
um
i
totally forgot the question original
question that you asked
right
so is there any piece of advice that you
would like to give um just a vague
piece of advice you know that just
appliable to
uh almost anything and everything
yeah many
one is i follow a rule of ten seconds
this is for anti-procrastination okay uh
you everybody wants to do something but
they're like are you calling it up and
it belongs so even i procrastinate
there's nothing wrong in it um but when
i know key up okay you need to have that
welcome now it's time to start how do
you start is the question where most
people fail because they don't know how
to go to the next level you do whatever
you can in 10 seconds
which means if you if it's about doing
homework
what can you do in those 10 seconds at
least you can bring out the notebook and
keep it on your table
so you do this place and you create a
visual cue for yourself a visual
milestone with the second book draw and
then go back to your netflix or whatever
you're watching okay at least next time
you wake up and you're moving around in
your area you will see that book being
kept there
and which was not there before
all you have to do is in that next 10
seconds is open the whenever you get
time open the first page and just read
it
and then you want to leave it let it be
so the thing is you every 10 second you
start
propelling yourself towards something if
i want to
clean the fan now fan cleaning is
difficult because you need elevation
which is not easy to come by
so all i can do is in 10 second is
keep a cloth or keep a chair under the
fan that's all and then go ahead so that
physical displacement
of an object in your space which either
come up
all you have to do is like climb up that
you can do in the next 10 seconds
all right so that is one
and uh and it also means in 10 seconds
you can write a note and keep it paste
it on your laptop
yeah or send a mail in 10 seconds so
about the second web joker
yeah
second is uh
if the new generation has to understand
what emotions are and what expression is
if you guys don't understand it uh one
thing is you will you will be losing a
lot of stuff uh from many angles you
will not know what to do when you are in
a conflict
whether it's somebody in a personal
conflict or a professional conflict with
because the thing is whenever you you're
in conflict uh fight or flight
mode
both ways
but the thing is uh we don't understand
you can also take it a middle path in
which you very calmly
address the question through
communication
yeah
and uh so because
previous earlier generation they had a
very big ego whenever conflict one would
go in conflict with them they would
either shut up or be aggressive
yeah
okay
and what we have to learn is key that's
not the way
if we
everybody's has a right to come to us
and say oh i do not like this about you
or what you have done
we should be okay with this question you
have to practice to not get baffled by
this question
yeah that p oh this person or this
friend of mine
uh some people who do it in private and
some people who do it publicly
now i'm not saying that everything that
is somebody is doing to us or saying to
us is correct that's okay
but if for example someone comes to me
publicly i would later on go and with
the same tone and communicate to them
look this was a personal matter between
me and you it should hardly have been
done in a more private setting okay
yeah
culture that's going on right now it's
very toxic
yeah
and i think uh
because it's not sarah communication
it's a very common thing to find people
are giving over online
yeah if you really have something good
to do then you will understand your time
is more precious
nothing good is going to come out from
an online debate
at all um
rather if you really want to do
something um
even if it is like
connecting people or donating even 10
rupees that's okay at least you're on
the action side talking side i think
coffee hogai
and on one way i or i'm also happy with
the culture of instagram people just
putting their random videos out i'm
saying that is still better because
previous generation
did not allow anyone to express so i'm
extremely happy that people are at least
expressing except
right
not everything is nice uh you must know
what to read what not to read what to
pay attention to what not to pay
attention to because there's too much
information anyways
definitely
work uh balance your emotions now how do
you balance it
balancing
you accept them you accept your anger
you accept your hate you accept your
sadness you accept except
right wherever you are right now
and then slowly like a layer peel by
peel make some little effort even
through a thought
to know
you know i am interested in my own
health physical mental and emotional
and therefore uh i would like to
keep the
better habits which resonate with me
and you know human body is the best uh
doctor you can say and even the best
instructor
clearly
i'm not comfortable with this
and you just have to feel it you just
have to feel am i comfortable am i not
comfortable even if you don't know the
reason why you're uncomfortable better
to take that caution
okay so when you're eating something
meeting someone doesn't matter
if you're not feeling well don't eat it
don't meet that person
and therefore you have to also
we also go through gluttony for example
like you know overeating and
even if you get that one question q i
think i am overeating at least
acknowledge that side also
because you have multiple voices
the more voice the kind of voices you
hear
you give more importance to them they
become stronger
okay so we have to listen to the right
voices and kind of give them also
acknowledgement and say okay i'll also
listen to you otherwise we'll be slave
to our own habits which is
which is not as cool because it's just
going to create more problem all the
time
so do you have any ambitious projects in
mind that you might have not done yet or
the most ambitious project that you have
done
oh no i don't
i don't know for people uh relatively
different projects will be you know for
people when they say
ambitious
because
for they will be different for different
people
for me also i generally keep
i do something and then i'm always
looking out for the next thing so i
don't pay too much attention to them
so i don't ponder overkill this is the
best object ever or project ever
and uh but i do would like to
drastically change the education system
that would be the biggest project ever
india or worldwide i think it it sucks
big time
right especially schooling because
college time planner you still have a
lot of choices
you don't want to attend you want to
attend you you have your own independent
lives there but schooling because
children are forced to do it
right we have created a system for them
and we are not giving them a choice
either
so vo system co improved
when you guys come into the college
first here
the potential that you have that has
been that has taken a very big hit
because of school education
and there are a lot of the very common
practices i would call them
now second is the culture of key you
need a particular
uh for example the boards the problem is
you can have alternate education before
but boards may just because that's a
single standardized paper which means
people who have who would like to have
different kind of schooling also don't
have a choice they will eventually have
to give the same standardized test
so happy people's problem are the whole
system is kind of designed and and
going by numbers if 25 000 people have
till now committed suicide
in and around because of the pressure of
education
then i think paying money to
for bad mental health that's the worst
system ever
and it's in return giving you a lot of
mental pressure
and you don't even feel you have learned
enough you don't feel confident about it
i think it's a lose-lose situation for
everyone
so yeah an education system cannot be
changed because there are millions of
people and
thousands of institutions all involved
playing their role and going by the
system
so
whether it's possible in one lifetime or
not i don't know but that is my aim
anyways
[Music]
so there are many like sites to social
media so obviously it gives you
opportunity to set like share your work
and
you know like communication everything
is there but
but like what do you say is the worst
of social media
i think worst of you all know
i have screen addiction personally
because i have adhd and therefore
screens offer you so much input so adsd
people possibly i don't know the
actual data around it but i do feel
um so that's one
basic con i'm also suffering from okay
and uh
but the thing is you have to see that
another con is fake news spreads too
quickly
okay people can get influenced too much
because what you have to understand is
social media maybe information
optimization already you want to believe
they understand your behavior profile
that's the whole that's the main
business of all social media
that they understand your
your mind profile because of your
choices you have made they know every
click you have in previous years you
have done every word you have chatted
they even your know your eye movement in
the screen they know you're
when you're scrolling what even if
you're stopping at a particular post for
a second or two they know it
and if you're scrolling through 10 posts
they know it
so the computer is doing the thinking it
creates a profile and through your
inputs and outputs it creates a profile
and therefore they will know oh you are
a person who gets agitated because of
this particular news
they will send you more news of that
okay
and therefore um that's a con side that
the social media is designed to keep you
dumb and and micro perspective although
it gives you very focused
perspective only
the way to undo it is pretty easy just
read a lot more from different websites
and you should also know which are
trust trustable media partners
and before forwarding anything you just
do a quick search
if that thing is not turning up in big
newspaper mata that's fake
right and the the good side is what you
have to understand is that you guys are
connected now that's the biggest
strength
with whatever cons that it has i'm
saying the biggest strength is it has
connected the youth um and you guys are
way more
faster with it you can
literally people have businesses on
instagram not a website also
right
yeah
so
i i also said the life is a full platter
right it's given to you you can use
whatever and you can also refuse
so now just because we are weak enough
to not take those choices we can't blame
the medium itself okay i'm not
advocating the
bat systems these all fall into bad
system which is um capitalism also you
know crony capitalism that they're
forcing you to buy more stuff but i
think it information
you should be now taking your own
choices and decisions yeah
i would say you cannot say oh we didn't
know you can google it
if you your laziness is not going to
save you from your accountability
so accountability is because now
accountability make your thank you
um
you are on spotlight but it also allows
you you can say okay i'm going to take
accountability but i'll do as i please
yeah all right
for example
even the actions of the government are
not accountable matlab
you know
so that's the kind of system we cannot
have we have to have a and we need to
develop this capability
i'll take this project and i'll be
accountable but i need my freedom then
of
thought a lot of people are trying to
escape from it but that will not lead
you to better intelligence that will
make you dumb if you want to act on
other people's
behalf
that monetary also passer-wise you'll
get a lot less
but the places where people come and say
i'll do it
i know i know my job i'll do it but i'll
do it in my own way there is high risk
for both parties but there is a lot more
benefit in both parties also
so one last question
so is there anything
that you would like to achieve uh or
your
goal
that you have set for yourself
um
i've kind of um
i've realized there are no
one thing that you need to do
so the thing is i've i've removed the
end frame if i say animation and it's a
story
i've removed the conclusion bit from my
life
i don't need the conclusion to end my
life do you understand
the reason is because i don't know how
short or how long it is
and therefore whatever i have done bef
while i was alive is good enough for me
so whatever if i my goal is also
education and changing education
whatever
minuscule percentage i'm able to change
it i'm good enough and i also realized
that it's like systems don't change in a
day it might take years and hundreds of
years also
all right so
again this kind of pragmatism you your
history you can read history and you can
decode it and you can understand how
changes happen there is no formula to it
um amazing people and
you know these characters come and they
make a big change but rather there are
these
lenient
developments that are happening
and uh and radical developments nobody
has control over you know game changer
just compose them
and therefore uh
in that sense in education what i
realized just if i can work with
students
i also call education the work of
working with consciousness which means
like for example i'm talking to you if
even one or two ideas hit you
your consciousness has been changed now
that's a permanent change
yeah and i don't and the that change
might reflect after 10 years once you
start working because once you start
working you have a lot more control over
your choices and decisions and you can
put money right
and therefore that change might even
come after 20 years so my project is
such that i'll see the result after 20
years or 15 years or 10 years there is
no way in me being able to see therefore
i like to meet students a lot more
and this talk is also happening from
that point of view
that
the thought can reach out and if it
gives even a single person of capability
to someone my job is done there yeah
yeah
um yeah that
was great um i learned a lot
from
whatever you said and yeah it was it was
a great session thank you so much for
joining me
um and yeah it was great thanks so much
thanks for thanks yeah
see you again
yeah starting this episode i'll see you
later um
thank you everyone for watching see you
later thank you thank you very much
[Music]